<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.311.4" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">
  <access order="allowFirst" authSystem="knb">
    <allow>
      <principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>EVOS data archiving project results: data, code and output (2016)</title>
    <creator id="1486521714777">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jessica</givenName>
        <surName>Couture</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of California, Santa Barbara</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Bren Hall</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty id="1508707672158">
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Colette</givenName>
        <surName>Ward</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, UCSB</organizationName>
      <role>Author</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty id="1508707715109">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Gavin</givenName>
        <surName>McDonald</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of California, Santa Barbara</organizationName>
      <role>Content Provider</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <references>1486521714777</references>
      <role>Originator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty id="1486521813973">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Matt</givenName>
        <surName>Jones</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, UCSB</organizationName>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty id="1508707626039">
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Rachael</givenName>
        <surName>Blake</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, UCSB</organizationName>
      <role>Author</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <abstract>
      <para>These data quantify  the results of a two year data archiving effort by a small group of researchers and students at the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis at UC Santa Barbara in collaboration with the Gulf Watch Alaska synthesis group and funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council (EVOSTC). The EVOSTC was formed following the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska in 1989. Since then, the EVOSTC has funded hundreds of projects and in 2012 we began a project to recover and archive the data collected during these EVOSTC funded projects. These data and analyses summarize the archiving project results and inform a manuscript (Funder imposed data publication requirements seldom inspire data sharing) in which we ask 5 main questions about the data collected from the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council funded projects:
1. Twenty-five years after the EVOS, for how many projects funded by EVOSTC can we collect data? 
2. Are there certain research fields that are more likely to make data available than others?
3. Are there certain sectors that are more likely to make data available than others?
4. Is the availability of data correlated to how old the data are? 
5. Why did people refuse to share their data?

The data here are a quantification of the responses to data outreach efforts, a data analysis script and results PDF as well as a figures script and output figures PDF.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
      <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
      <keyword>oil spill</keyword>
      <keyword>data</keyword>
      <keyword>archiving</keyword>
      <keyword>recovery</keyword>
      <keyword>open science</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This material is based upon work funded by the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis (NCEAS)and the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council (EVOSTC).  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit to EVOS and NCEAS any additional funding agencies should be followed when using this data. Please let the Owner know when this data is used.

This data is licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Gulf of Alaska, Alaksa</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-159.8752</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-121.65</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>61.77312</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>43.83333</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1989</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2010</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <references>1486521714777</references>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Data recovery and archiving</title>
            <para>From 2012 to 2014, a team of one full-time and three part-time staff members was assigned to collect and archive data funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council (EVOSTC) targeting specifically those projects funded between 1989 and 2010. Project information was obtained from the projects page on the EVOSTC website, which includes varying levels of detail for each project, ranging from project title only to full bibliographic information and attached reports. We tracked the progress of the data request and acquisition process for each project based on six stages: “emailed”, “replied”, “sent data”, “data revised”, “published”, “unrecoverable”. Contact information was obtained through agency sites and Google searches based on the information we were able to gather from the EVOSTC site. If we were able to find contact information for the listed principal investigator (either email address or phone number), an outreach email or phone call was made explaining the data recovery project and requesting data for the project in question. Projects for which outreach could be made were labeled “emailed”. If we then received a reply to the outreach and could therefore confirm that the contact information was correct, the project label was promoted to “replied”, regardless of level of cooperation expressed in the response. Once we received data from for a project, the label was changed to “data sent”. Since it was often difficult to determine how much data were created under each project, if any data were received the project was considered successful. If the data were clean and well documented enough and/or the contact was responsive enough to guide us through any necessary data edits and metadata creation the data were labeled “data formatted”. Once the contact approved our edits and compiled metadata, the products were then published to the Gulf of Alaska Historic Data Portal and the project was labeled, “published”.</para>
            <para>Since each funded project had an unknown number of “datasets”, we base success on the publication of at least on dataset for any given project, regardless of size or complexity. Throughout our extensive data recovery effort, we took careful notes of our out reach efforts, communications and progress in publicly archiving acquired data for use in statistical analyses.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Statistical analysis</title>
            <para>At the close of the data collation effort, we quantified the number of projects that fell into each of the above status labels and plotted them in a simple bar chart in order to assess the final status of our archiving undertaking.</para>
            <para>Results of the outreach efforts are further characterized based on three project descriptors: research field of the project (field), agency sector of the home institution of the principal investigator (sector), age of data when data when recovery efforts were initiated (age). Age of data is calculated as the number of years since the last year a project received EVOSTC funding since some projects spanned multiple years.</para>
            <para>The impacts of these characteristics on the likelihood of providing data are assessed using discrete statistical tests: Chi-squared and random forest analyses. Chi-squared tests were run on each group of characteristics individually to test for differences in success based on these classifications. We then asked which of these characteristics were the most important in determining if the data from a project will successfully be recovered. To assess the relative importance of the three characteristics we ran a random forest analysis using the “party” package in the R programming language. We also produced one classification tree to visualize how these characteristics affect our outcome.</para>
            <para>Also of interest were the reasons data were not recovered. To quantify these responses we categorized the projects for which we were unable to gather any data based on notes from our correspondences.  The projects included in this analysis include those labeled “emailed”, “replied” and “unrecoverable” in the status categorization. Projects in the category “replied” were instances where we received at least an initial reply confirming that we had accurate contact information but lost communication before the data was sent. These projects have been re-categorized here as communication lost. Of the “unrecoverable” projects, notes were used to divide these into: no contact information, data lost, non-digital data, unwilling to share, and requested additional funding. The projects from the “emailed” status have been added to the no contact information group since we were never able to confirm the outreach efforts actually reached the target recipient. Data are only labeled data lost if our contact confirmed that they were so. Similarly, the non-digital data, unwilling to share and requested additional funding cases are only labeled as such for projects were data requests were rejected for these confirmed reasons. Non-digital data is deemed “unrecoverable” here since our project lacked the resources to convert or store such data. We have since converted these data, when possible, and refer to these data in the discussion.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Gulf Watch Alaska</title>
      <personnel>
        <references>1486521813973</references>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>
        <para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</para>
      </funding>
    </project>
    <dataTable id="1486524600429">
      <entityName>evosArchResults.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Tracked results of data archiving effort</entityDescription>
      <physical id="1486523927327">
        <objectName>evosArchResults.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="byte">28350</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/urn:uuid:007f82b9-bc30-43d3-9cf3-8cce9f00101a</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute id="1486524600430">
          <attributeName>Status</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Final status of the EVOS project recovery for given project. Each row represents a separate project</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Replied</code>
                    <definition>contact information confirmed and data request was received</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Emailed</code>
                    <definition>initial outreach was sent</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Unrecoverable</code>
                    <definition>data is not recoverable</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>SentData</code>
                    <definition>data were obtained for the given project but were not published</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>published</code>
                    <definition>metadata was created and data were published</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Published</code>
                    <definition>metadata was created and data were published</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600431">
          <attributeName>category</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>research field subject of the given project</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>research field</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600433">
          <attributeName>start</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Year the given project first received funding</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600434">
          <attributeName>end</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Last year the given project received funding</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600435">
          <attributeName>secondaryCat</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>secondary categorization of the project</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>secdonary category</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600436">
          <attributeName>reason</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Reason given for projects deemed "unrecoverable"</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>reason unrecoverable</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600437">
          <attributeName>agency</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Home agency of the project's PI</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>home agency</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600438">
          <attributeName>ecosystem</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Ecosystem in which the project occured withing the larger Gulf of Alaska system.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>project ecosystem</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600439">
          <attributeName>dataType</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Data field classification for the project</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>data field</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="1486524600440">
          <attributeName>project</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>internal project label</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>label</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>324</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>MS figures R markdown script</entityName>
      <entityDescription>R markdown script that plots the data (evosArchResults.csv) representing total results and data field, agency and temporal breakdowns.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>ecoinfoPlots.Rmd</objectName>
        <size unit="byte">18464</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>application/octet-stream</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution id="1486524739435">
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/urn:uuid:74e94655-db70-43ca-badb-5d934ab67fbb</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>Other</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>MS figures PDF</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Output PDF from MS figures R markdown script</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>ecoinfoPlots.pdf</objectName>
        <size unit="byte">234827</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>application/pdf</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution id="1486524795335">
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/urn:uuid:179a36cf-1eae-427c-b2bb-0c711c8e8fbc</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>Other</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>Data analysis R markdown script</entityName>
      <entityDescription>R markdown script for statistical analysis of evosArchResults.csv data</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>dataAnalysis.Rmd</objectName>
        <size unit="byte">7511</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>application/octet-stream</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution id="1486525122750">
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/urn:uuid:95f49c46-4c0e-4dce-ae89-ee6e06b95d32</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>Other</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>Data analysis PDF</entityName>
      <entityDescription>PDF output from Data analysis R markdown script with statistical results</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>dataAnalysis.pdf</objectName>
        <size unit="byte">232120</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>application/pdf</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution id="1486525180151">
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/urn:uuid:ac458cc0-0fc2-4f9b-ac72-81f3e0656b6a</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>Other</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
